hello
and welcome to actin flab this is the
active inference live stream
number 20.1 on april 20th
2021 so a lot of repeating digits
and i'm looking forward to this
conversation with all of you so thanks
for joining
welcome to the active inference lab
everyone we're a participatory online
lab
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference
you can find us at the links that are on
this slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following
good video etiquette for live streams
like muting when we're not talking and
raising our hands so we can hear from
everyone on the stack
hello greetings today in number 20.1
we're in the first of
two discussions that we're going to be
having as a group
regarding this paper the emperor's new
markov blankets
and so the goal of these discussions is
to learn
discuss be curious and find out how we
got here and where we're going and
why we're doing that and we're just
going to be having a nice
conversation with the authors which are
we're just really appreciative that
they've joined
so we're gonna just go to the
introductions and warm up
and then we will just be able to jump
around and see where
the conversation takes us so i'm daniel
and i'm in california i will pass it to
shannon
hey i'm shannon i'm usually in
california but i'm in south dakota since
the pandemic
are we going straight into warm-up
questions or just names in around the
room you can say hello or give a warm-up
thought
okay um yeah so i'm excited today
i'm excited to
explore whether or not we can use markov
blankets to describe
groups of people and social dynamics
and i tried to do this in a project
before and abandoned it pretty quickly
and reading this paper i think if i had
taken the pearl blanket formulation
which i'm sure we'll get into talking
about later
it would have been a lot more helpful so
i'm excited to discuss that today
um i'll pass that to steven
hello steven steven here i'm in toronto
and um it's nice to be here and thanks a
lot for this paper because i think it's
going to be really interesting to have
all these bits of the jigsaw
put together and i'm actually quite
interested in the paper because
i'm trying to work out when to use the
concepts of like the markov blanket to
help
describe processes and when just to
maybe talk about hidden states
and not focus so much on the the blanket
part so
that's quite useful for me and i will
pass it over to dave
i'm dave i am in baguio city oh
120 miles north of manila it's the
blazing summer time
we're a mile high city so it might get
as high as 80 degrees
fahrenheit i'm retired from information
technology and my background is in the
cybernetics of learning and teaching
great and we have two authors here
so maybe first we'll go to chris and
then yela
and just feel free to introduce yourself
the project the collaboration
however you'd like thank you so
thanks a lot for inviting us i'm
christolega i'm currently a postdoc
at the rural universitat in bochum
germany
i'm joining from berlin though and
i'm currently working on a research
grant
on bayesian cognition and
and the conspiracy theories i'm
specifically
interested in how proponents of
conspiracy theories
discount new evidence that contradicts
their beliefs
and this paper from my perspective grew
out of a
really long i guess friendship with
yellow we can
say that we've met a long time ago
at a conference in the netherlands in
2014 i believe on bayesian cognition
and we were both fascinated by this new
uh theory framework of predictive
processing
and i remember that already there there
was a seed of some kind of
doubt in me or or kind of a worry
planted because
it was a it was a conference on
probabilistic approaches to cognition
everyone there was supposed to be a
bayesian in one way or another
and suddenly it turned out that
basically no one agrees with
each other and everyone uses the terms
in a different way and i feel like
this paper is in a way um
contextualizing that experience for for
us
but yeah sorry i'll let yella speak now
okay uh great samuel abraham
um i work at macquarie university in
sydney
but then also due to pandemic reasons
located in amsterdam
uh the netherlands um
and so my my new research project is on
the philosophical foundations of the
attention economy but my phd was really
in
in uh in on a free energy principle
and an embodied cognition um
and indeed this this paper grew
out of a group of people who are or
colleagues and friends and and
and acquainted with each other's work
all roughly on
on predictive processing and and free
energy principle and active inference
but from slightly different
uh uh directions uh and i think it was
sparked by kind of combination of
fmsa kind of curiosity and skepticism
about some of the developments that
that were that were happening and have
been happening already since a long time
since since i guess 2013 or 14
when some of these papers originally
came out and kind of slowly got taken up
in more and more heavy philosophical
projects
and i think the more and more we read
those papers the more and more we grew
interested and and skeptical at the same
time
and uh this was really a project to try
to finally kind of
uh uh nail down what what was bugging us
and and how perhaps how it might be
salvaged or
or or what to do um
so i'm happy this is now pre-printed i'm
very happy we get to discuss this i was
this morning
doing the dishes and on my headphones
listening to your exposition of of my
paper
and that was just a very great and
mind-blowing uh
experience where somebody explicated
those ideas and not being one of the
artists i think that's that's on the
other
all of us that's that's just fantastic
to to have happen
i think actually there is a third author
latent uh
there um so i'll try to pass on the
baton to manuel and see if he does
anything or responds
otherwise we discontinue well hello
everyone
uh i'm just here trying to look around
for a little bit
it's uh past 11 p.m in tokyo
where i'm right now so yeah i'll try to
you know stay um along for a bit but
yeah clearly i'll leave the other two
guys
like who are much fresher than me right
now to to lead the discussion
um as for me i i have more of a
background i guess in
computer science some maths here and
there
now i'm doing some work on
control theory and estimation
theory applied to neuroscience
a lot of methods uh probably right now
and
which is the main reason i guess i
started working on
active inference and related ideas and
yeah as
the other two guys have already um said
you know this paper
was kind of born out of you know around
our own curiosity
and you know questions regarding like
what
the framework actually does and what it
can do and what it cannot do
so you know then i'll leave yellow to
you know
leave the discussion from here on
awesome thanks everyone for joining it's
great to have
just the authors and and kind of read
between the citations
and then actually enliven between the
citations so that we can ask questions
that were maybe
alluded to and hear your fresh
perspectives what kind of feedback
you've gotten on the paper
etc so yeah yeah where would you like to
start otherwise there's just a bunch of
places we can jump in
great um i'll just briefly
uh give some introductory uh uh comments
uh uh i'll keep it brief because i think
we're all roughly on the same
page having read the paper um
so as i was saying uh this this project
got
started out from a combination of
curiosity and skepticism about the
some new applications of active
inference
and free energy principle and so i think
as i understood it before
it's it was a kind of functional lens to
try to understand cognitive systems
and in that sense offering a kind of
unifying perspective and also it's a
different cognitive constructs in the
cognitive sciences
and i was already kind of very
interested in that and what we've
what what we've seen in the in in the
last few years i think
are one applications or at least
attempts to apply it to kind of
the harder questions so the hard
question of consciousness intentionality
etc which is more than this kind of
functional lens
an application to systems that are not
necessarily cognitive
so living systems as a whole
or even like a global global systems or
social systems
and then as well using this terminology
not only
to as a functional lens to to understand
systems that you already deem cognitive
but also
to use those tools themselves to do
democratic work
uh so to decide what is
a living or another living system what
is a cognitive or another cognitive
system so to somehow
employ those tools of active influence
onto these kind of questions
um and i think we were yeah we were all
interested in in in in a set of
questions
and and seeing how that would uh uh uh
um
how that could work and whether those
arguments really
uh really hold um
and i think to do that we needed to have
a combination of
uh one conceptual arguments uh two
formal
arguments and three philosophical uh uh
analysis and and
kind of combine those in the same paper
and i think that makes it also
made it a very challenging paper to to
to write to see how all these different
parts of the paper fit
together and and perhaps it's also made
it a challenging paper to to read but
we'll probably get to that in
a moment um and there's i mean there's
something
here i think that that kind of blocks
the whole uh uh
field uh some of us were on just uh a
few hours ago on social media and there
there's a new paper
uh now uh among others by decoding polo
and
evan thompson randall beer and
i think one of the more meta discussions
was was like how much mathematics how
much conceptual
work do you need to actually contribute
to the more conceptual
uh questions you want to to ask and i
think that this is something that's
intrinsically intentioned here
within the literature that you kind of
need to have a very technical
understanding
to to have to watch this question in the
first place but then
if you do that perhaps you lose out on
the more conceptual issues or you you
lose out
also part of your readership because
it's it's it's only a few people that
understand it so there's something
exciting there about fep as a whole
and i think we tried at least to be um
as accessible as possible in in writing
this paper while at the same time
supporting our arguments with with with
with
the formalism that we thought were were
necessary and that
uh ultimately brought us to to writing
this
and the thing
in in the moment we have a lot of
pre-prints that came out in the last
few months all kind of trying to target
and trying to to
to to to to criticize these these
developments in any principle
so i think some of you some of them
you've discussed here already
so from mel anderson papers thomas
as a good paper on this as well along
with the thompson paper
so i'm really curious to see how in the
next few months
half years say this this debate will uh
will
will will point out i think there's a
number of really interesting kind of
proposals now
and uh yeah also um
keep checking this uh this lab to
to see how you treat those other papers
i'm really looking forward to that
cool um very interesting blue do you
want to just
say hi give any introductory thoughts if
you'd like sure good morning
i'm blue knight i'm an independent
research consultant from new mexico and
i really enjoyed this paper um i don't
know if you got to see like our
contextualization video but
it was really good
cool so i'll be kind of taking some
notes everybody can also jump into the
document and that was a big question
that you raised there yellow um how much
mathematics is required to understand or
work with
free energy principle and active
inference and then which
are the sort of skeletal elements and
the sinews so to speak of the math
and then which parts might be secondary
or not
up
for some reason there might be a few
seconds of uh of uh
just flipping but yes sorry just yeah
what um
elements of the math are required to
understand and work with
these topics and then of course the
major
question of your paper and some of these
other recent papers we've discussed is
whatever the mathematics are what kinds
of philosophical or metaphysical
claims can we reach validly or or
invalidly um
yeah any other big questions or thoughts
people can just raise their
hand with a little bottom left icon so
yeah we'll do
steven and then blue
yeah just one thing building on the bit
what daniel said there is
active inference in biological systems
could be present
as a way for life to
function and evolve but there's also
possibilities that
the active influence process could
create structures or networks
which then form other systems which may
not have to be
so based on ergodicity in the same way
it might be like you have the skeletal
system
which gives you locomotion so i suppose
in some ways
i'd be interested in that way that
you know we're not tied to everything
being active inference in terms of how
we can
understand its applications even though
maybe at the core
it has to be there at some level
cool thanks anyone can give a thought on
that or blue
go for it so
um just to kind of yeah to i don't know
so stephen what you just said like
active inference is
present in biological systems i think
you know we need to be careful before we
pick a side
over instrumentalism versus realism like
is active inference present in a living
system
maybe not maybe it's just the way that
we use to represent a living system or
to model a living system or
like our best guess so far right i mean
i think that the way that the science
evolves
um you know in terms of how we think
about biological systems processing
information
will you know i mean active inference is
what we have now but it probably won't
be what we have in 100 years
if we survive 100 years but but my
question was
uh you know in reading the paper i
really it was brought to my attention
and and steven's question
so perfectly illustrates this so so to
there's a great degree of semantics
that's involved
um and our choice of language i think
really shapes
how we um perceive the intentions of
others
so it's just is that is that the caution
or is that the tale or is that the
cd underbelly of the paper or to what
role do you really think that language
a lot of these things could be fixed
with language
yes cool yellow you want to go for it
and then shannon is your hand
great so i'll um in the those are two
two great questions um and just to to
clarify the the last one
um when you say uh language do you mean
the kind of
concepts that we are uh using
or language as a whole as a system
so i i mean like how steven just said
you know
systems have active inference like it's
just like systems have active inference
like
i have a heart and a kidney and a liver
but i don't know that i necessarily have
active inference right so it's just our
choice of of language
in in that so not language as a whole
but but language like
carefully selected word choice could
maybe prevent a lot of the
the conflict um
yeah i i i think so and then i guess
generally you you might think that lots
of philosophy is actually a kind of
a linguistic therapy right
you're just trying to very be very
concise and using the right kind of
terminology so that you don't
slip into confusions that that then will
cloud your thinking also
uh so i think there's definitely some of
that on
the on on the background in the in in
this paper
um but it's it's it's not only a
language right there's also the the the
formal models
uh and and how to interpret those those
those formal models
um and there
in in the translation between the
technical use
uh um of of of this terminology
and the kind of everyday intuitions it
gives us i think there is in this room
for a lot of mistakes and slippage i
mean the notion of blanket is one right
i mean
i have a blanket on my bed and that has
that has a spatial dimension and so and
you can be either
on top of it or below it etc and and so
when you then use the notion of a markov
blanket this is the first intuition that
people will will
have uh and it turns out that actually
no
these kind of things don't have such a
kind of existence right they don't they
actually they don't they're not really
spatial
things in the world they're they are
just aspects of mathematical model
and so indeed in in kind of there the
language is one but also just a
particular way in which you understand
your concepts either as everyday things
or as technical things i think that
there's a lot of those slippages there
and i guess
the whole literature is full with
notions of model of
inference and and then it's very unclear
whether something is a
inference it's a technical notion or
inference as a philosophy of mind notion
or inference is something else
um so yeah there there are a lot of
those those
those uh things in the background
and i think that that also uh points to
the question that stephen was
asking uh in terms of like we can think
about
the structures for locomotion and so
like how does this relate to to active
inference
um and so this is this is i guess this
is i mean perhaps this is a topic that's
not really there in
in in in in this paper uh so much but
there there's a
huge literature in active influence on
how to understand the notion of model
and whether agents are models of the
environment
and one way to see that is is thinking
like well there is an
an and an echo niche around this and we
have
through selection that might not might
not be uh
understood for active inference have
been equipped with a particular kind of
neural system particular kind of body
that allows us to to engage with it with
that environment and in that sense kind
of
things like the the the structures that
facilitate locomotion could be just as
part
just just as well be part of that model
but then model in a very different sense
as it's typically used in cooking
designs
um yeah so so that that's also that
that's very much how you understand
model uh uh
really um shapes how you will answer
these kind of questions about how active
inference and locomotion also
relate to each other thanks for that
and um it's almost like the word
semantic
ironically carries a double meaning
because people will dismiss
a discussion well that's a semantic
discussion on one sense they mean you're
talking about words words words like
you're kind of just saying random stuff
we're debating about a word we're
talking about the same thing it's
semantic it's only semantic
but semantics are meaning and so i i
think i've
blipped out or maybe for some people for
a second but it's just so funny how
semantic refers to both the big sense of
meaning
and the small sense of the word and
we're all reducing our uncertainty
by actually going into the details what
is the markov versus the pearl versus
the fristen
blanket and can we just have a common
reference point
so that when somebody says i'm using
frist and blanket in the sense of this
paper
then it will preempt some of these
broader
valid or sort of spurious questions
so cool shannon and then anyone else who
raises their hand
yeah so i'll try to make this comment
without too much
rambling um but we talked with
with mel um andrews with an s um
hippolyta and thomas venice and we've
been
discussing like on what level the
system implements active inference or
is um has markov blankets
in the system versus when it's useful
for us to describe it that way so that
realism
versus instrumental debate and
something that was came up in the
conversation with an s something that's
easy for me
is to claim that there is no markov
blanket necessarily in a group of people
that are interacting
if we look at clusters of fans in a
stadium i might as a researcher identify
this cluster of fans because they're
interacting in a certain way with each
other that's different from this other
cluster of fans
and some game event happens and that
ends up being some sort of coupling
parameter
and now we can describe this as one um
unified system one unified cluster of
fans of people um and i am pretty happy
with saying that there is not a
real boundary in the world between group
a
group b or that emerges over um the
larger group c but
i really want to say that that happens
in the brain
and i really want to say that our like
the neurons in our brains are
interpreting the world as if there are
boundaries and that's forming boundaries
on neural processes
um like there's this specific people are
talking about manifolds a lot lately and
there's this similar
um fuzziness and what it means to be a
neural manifold but like there's a
certain
manifold that's associated with
observing this feature of the world
and i wonder if you have any
intuitions from this distinction
can we can we be realist about
markov blankets or the fringe principle
or active inference as applied to
neural states i mean that's where these
theories started while being
anti-realist about
applying these two dynamics in the world
like groups of people
great question also um just a technical
note like i'm not sure what's happening
with the active inference youtube or
jitsi or whatever
but clearly my internet is working
because we're having the video call
but the stream glitched so we can just
continue not on live stream and then
i'll just re-upload the full
quality and it won't have any glitches
so i'll figure it out for next week but
it's all good it won't be um
fully live but we can just still think
of it the same way which is the vast
majority of people
viewing it anyway so yeah sorry about
that i'll figure it out for next time
but um thanks shannon for the question
about the groups so
anyone want to speak to the group
question
and about whether groups can be properly
said to be
having or uh modeled by these blankets
or where where
is that
sorry david you so i mean daniel you you
glitched for a second
and uh yeah in the meanwhile yell asked
if i want to answer the group
question and i think i would actually i
have some thoughts about this so
i think one important thing about the
free energy
framework that especially how it's been
developed recently
is that people often like
people infristance closed circle like
ines hippolyta for example
has caused the paper recently with him
about markov blankets
in which they talk about viewing
different systems as agents
so so they talk about a neuron as an
agent right they talk about the whole
organism as an agent
and and it kind of scaffolds across
multiple
time scales and and
spatial scales and i think
our paper leaves it open to some extent
leaves the question open whether there
is some kind of scale
on which if we fix the parameters of the
model
the models can be validated and they can
produce new predictions or new
new empirical findings in such a way
where we would be
forced to accept that perhaps on that
particular scale there really
are blankets in the fristen sense or
like
at least that these models are so good
at
predicting certain events or findings or
phenomena
on a given scale that we would be
inclined to give them a realist
interpretation so i think this is still
on the table and it's very much
open it's just that given the
ambitions and the scope of the free
energy framework
uh and the fact that they start with
this assumption of viewing
different systems on different scales as
agents
right now it's just not really clear
um which level so to speak
the this this way of framing phenomena
would be validated in a realist context
great um really what warrants
or what license is what evidence would
we need for realist interpretations
and it's not even just a yes no because
there's kind of a few
kinds of realism as you pointed out like
there's different notions of boundary
and so a group might be very well said
to have an informational boundary
like this jitsi people who are not in
the jitsi are not part of this
informational boundary
but then in some other sense the group
may not fall so neatly under the
definition of
a realist interpretation of a blanket um
manuel
yeah so uh i was a bit slow i guess
after
stephen and blue actually asked um a
couple of questions earlier so i'm
briefly gonna go back to that and then
try to
reconnect to what shannon uh was
actually talking about
so um as for
i guess the the loose sense in which we
might want to interpret
active inference i think there is i
don't know
relatively low risk in just
i don't know waving our hands and saying
the systems
do some sort of active inference as long
as
we know we keep it loose losing such a
way that
in my opinion you might just lose
entirely like any meaning
we're just saying well you know there's
some active inference happening there in
the same sense that there is some
active inference happening in i don't
know
planets orbiting around stars or
galaxies uh
having some particular physical behavior
and
and so we might end up just not having
anything to say
it's safe but it's also not very
useful in a sense so in that direction i
think that our work
is trying to you know
uh go in the direction where we want to
say what active inference is
not in a way it is important to say well
you know this is what it is right now
and this is what it cannot be and if you
want it to be something else well you
you have to tell me exactly what else
you need
for that thing to even work to begin
with and then related to that there's
also
um so i think i might have heard this
from
alex shuntz before and i don't know who
else before him might have mentioned
this
um the idea of say an active inference
coming from the
i don't know highway and an active
inference coming from a more normal
if we can call it like that path the
highway is what fristen has been trying
to do more recently
you know starting from first principles
as he claims like from the physics
of you know langevin equations and you
know stochastic systems
and then trying to say derive notions
that are
already established in non-equilibrium
physics
and from there get all the way to say a
definition of what agents
might be there is also say the
the i don't know the normal way which i
think is what uh
shannon alluded to um you know at some
point because you know
this active inference theory was
originally brought out in neuroscience
with no ambition to be a first principle
theory starting from you know
uh launch of integrations that might
describe any physical system
in this universe it was just supposed to
be some sort of helpful framework
that in some way was going to generalize
reinforcement learning
which is an absolutely fair i guess uh
goal and ambition
but has also nothing to do with all of
the physics
that is more recently being plugged into
active inference
and one could safely go say the the
second route and just forget about all
the physics it might
leave it i don't know to a different um
i don't know to a different status but
it would still be
potentially useful and it would still be
something that we might look forward to
and that i guess lead me to
um leads me to um something that shannon
was mentioning about
manifolds and in some sense
um you know the the question about you
know are markov
blankets real or not is similar to
yes are manifolds real or not
um and here you know i don't want to say
um i'm not really sure you know how to
to go about this in in the same way that
i don't know
physicists generally don't think too
much about
well you know is this energy landscape
real or not
is my you know is my ball actually
trying to fall to the ground or is it
just
well you know it is a good metaphor it
works really well
we tend to use some you know a genitive
language in there
but i guess that if you hard press a
physicist you will
probably hardly get an answer about you
know oh is this energy escape
like real is there any an energy scape
inside the ball
that the ball is using to actually roll
down the hill
well probably no it is the kind of
question that you know
well i will still be using lagrange
mechanics i will still be using
emiletonia mechanics but i will not be
you know opening up a ball looking for
the energy landscape there
in the same way i will still be using
manifolds well personally because you
know population codes are
revealing like to to be pretty useful in
neuroscience
but i will not say like start looking
inside the brain like well where's the
manifold there
if that makes sense
yes totally makes sense and real and
useful
when they're aligned people celebrate
and when they're not aligned there's
often another story
why something is still really useful
even though it's just a useful
fiction or something like that and i
think that
um vector alignment is really what we
want to nuance we want to have like an
hour hand and a second hand in a minute
hand we want to be clear
where are we just specifying a partially
observable
markov decision process and fitting data
and then where are we in the
interpretive
frame and where are we in a metaphysical
frame even beyond the um
interpretive steven and then anyone else
raising their hand
i think as well as where we say if it's
real or not there's the sense of
at what scales and i like the fact that
you talked about scales is
what scales um and at those scales how
much plausibility
is there for certain types of inference
processes to be possible
i suppose that's where you know if
there's no ergodicity present
or seems to be very little at certain
scales then maybe
it's less likely that that mechanism is
an active inference mechanism although
there may be some elements of it
so i think that that also changes the
way that the realist
aspect could be brought in it's like how
much could it be a blanket
aspect or maybe like you say that
other scales unlike say a single cell
which is diffusing
chemicals over a membrane and there'd be
some weak mixing process going on
there's
some um yeah there's some ways that
variation or expected free energy
are not the only mechanisms
even suggesting that it's a mechanism is
something that's mechanical
it's these are what we want to
understand and these are the discussions
and then are they equivalent and do
mechanisms have to be real things
or can a mechanism be something that
doesn't exist in the world
or a conceptual mechanism or could it be
just a pattern
that doesn't exist in one measurable
thing we can put on a scale
like a machine um so cool questions
dave and then anyone else raising their
hands
okay uh sometimes the math
is trusted too far and it's allowed to
do
a whole lot of work but sometimes the
math gets crippled
now i'm a student of gordon pasque and
cyclicity
and um self-stabilizing feedback is
really critical to everything he did in
learning theory and biology
system science and what's the very first
thing you do when you mention
markov processes you stomp out the
cycles you rip out those cycles you're
just not allowed to have loops
in a markov network well then they come
back in because that's what people are
looking for they're looking for
self-stabilization
and using the environment and the
environment using you to enrich itself
and
and then as you point out at the end of
your paper well then
dr fristin finds there's cycles in there
and then he goes and rips them out all
over again
what has anybody ever just left the
cycles in
come up with a formalism that's richer
than
a markovian tree
and then see if maybe things get easier
and simpler
great question dave and i think
the big question is what are the inputs
what do we want to get
out of this math are we looking to make
analytical
claims or are we looking to have uh very
general
frameworks for control theory um or for
estimation
theory even like manuel mentioned so
anyone can raise their hand but um chris
uh thanks so i just wanted to follow up
on the
last two questions but i see that
there's already a theme emerging in a
way
so one thing is about the maths and you
know
already the question that was posed at
the beginning how much
the understanding of maths informs
research that people can do into the
predictive processing
framework and i think and now we return
to this question in a way
with this question of of cycles and the
fact that we actually
analyze you know we leave the cycles out
and i think it's
in some ways useful to think about
our paper in many ways and and what's
happening with the free energy
framework as a kind of a pyramid where
you know formalisms mathematical
formalisms are stacked
one on another and finally the free
energy principle really
lies at the top and what we've been
trying to do in some ways is to
lead our readers you know through the
steps
going up to the free energy principle
and like
how it's supposed to work but the thing
is that of course there are
many different ways to get there so you
know someone might have
like you you can think about the cycles
like the the
the topological method that we took with
with
directed uh graphs and
the the the way of thinking about
dynamical
coupled systems and loops and stuff like
that you can think about this as
different slopes of the same pyramid
right
in the end the point is to that you want
to get to the free energy principle
exactly you want to get to the free
energy principle
and the free energy principle lies on
top of
a lot of work done in many different
formal fields
and i think that i think that the the
the last
question asked by dave pointing to the
possibility that perhaps
if we leave the question of directed the
cyclical graphs aside and just focus
on cyclical systems perhaps we could
arrive at a new con
formal construct that could later turn
out to be
somewhat equivalent to to a mark
of blankets but wouldn't be so easily
conflated with mark of blankets i think
that's a very interesting possibility
uh that probably should be explored in
the literature
um and the other thing i wanted to just
address very briefly is the fact that
the other theme that seems to be
emerging here in the discussion is this
theme of
patterns and and what's real and what's
not real and i think here it's useful to
bring back uh or or kind of points that
dan dennett has already done some
important work in the past on this
with his work on real patterns and and
what does it mean for a pattern to be
real
and what's the difference between a
pattern being real or and not being real
right
um one interesting thing if we think
about active inference for example is
that if we think about the social
dynamics
uh we can think for example about the
dynamics in the army
right a platoon clearly has
some kind of a blanket like the platoon
is trying to maintain its homeostasis
they they are all trying to stay alive
especially in a hostile environment
far away from the equilibrium right the
interesting thing about
the example of a platoon if i and i hope
i'm not
getting that wrong now but i'm sure
manuel would correct me if i do
is that we don't actually assume that
the the that the
platoon would be statistically ergodic
because it
definitely shouldn't uh shouldn't
visit some of its possible state spaces
right
portions of the of its state space like
the whole point of putting people into a
platoon is so that
they won't visit certain regions of the
state space
um so those are
interesting questions here and of course
the question about like are platoons
real
uh you know are they uh
it's an interesting it's an interesting
question to ponder
dan dennett previously has asked the
question about money right so is the
value of money real
obviously it has direct impact on our
lives we be it has a direct impact on
how we behave uh in virtue of the
kind of social construct and the social
scaffolding
uh on which it rests but we all kind of
agree that
you know the the existence of value of
money is just a
it's just some kind of a fiction that we
all buy into
especially now that the gold parity is
no longer a thing
nice cool points and and
it's really remarkable how this what is
real i mean in some sense it makes sense
it's the classic
philosophy question plato's cave and
what's real
and it's hard to differentiate it
sometimes because it's used in very many
senses so sometimes like the pyramid
it's almost like we're surfacing it
like an iceberg to mix metaphors and
then people can
visibly attack a formalism well the
directed acyclic graph doesn't represent
reality because reality has cyclic
elements
and then we have to sort of change the
formalism a little bit
like could we run it in a sequential way
could a message passing algorithm
emulate a cyclic system even though
locally computationally it's linearized
but you lose some other attribute is
that real then would the model be real
so fun questions um yella and then
stephen
great um so i think a question kind of
related slash orthogonal to uh to to to
the real question is a question about
uh what's in the paper called
reification right so it's it's a fact
that
if you make a mathematical formalization
of something that mathematical
formalization might
is quite often idealization of the
target phenomenon that you're that
you're investigating
and then as long as you treat that
mathematical structure as an
idealization
of the target phenomenon and don't
automatically transfer the properties of
the idealization to the to the target
phenomenon then that's completely fine
and then the uh where it gets
upside down is if you suddenly take that
mathematical formulization as somehow
being
at the root of the appearance of the
target phenomenon that you're
investigating
so we make this case for for the kind of
graphical model uh
example where there is a complicated
system you make a graphical model of it
which is you know by all means a kind of
simplification of that very system
and then if you start to say look markov
blankets were actually in that system
you're also implying that no actually
that mathematical idealization uh of of
of
of of the system was actually already in
the target system that you were that
you're investigating and that's that's
the thing
else will move that you make the
mathematics itself more
real than you're than you're supposed to
make it um
and of course i think we said this
towards the end of the paper you
you can buy the bullet right and say
like look no matt reality at this very
core is mathematical
so so so we're fine but that that is
something that doesn't itself come from
the formalism but requires actually a
pretty strong metaphysical assumptions
and so the question about in that sense
the question about the reality of a
mathematical structure is also
intertwined with this question about
reification about how do you
see the relationship between the target
phenomenon you're investigating
and the mathematical formalization of
the target phenomenon
i think these two questions kind of go
go go ahead and then
thank you steven than anyone else
yeah i think this this mathematical
piece is important as well because i
think there's often the assumption
that we're always inferring this model
of the world and how to
adapt and interact with the world but
one of the key things
particularly higher order animals and
humans like the platoon
is at times they want to be disordered
or this coherent self but
ultimately when they're in the field yes
they want to get into the most optimal
ways to shoot and do things but they
need to
gain the system they need to not do what
the other people think they're going to
do
and they have to guess what someone else
might do which is non-ergodic something
which is
you're basically gaming each other's
environment so that you're
basically like prey and predator you're
you're also then taking another stance
so you step outside of
what would be that normal dynamical free
energy
minimization process and that is sort of
sitting on top
of the other process so i think that's a
kind of an interesting
confusion cool
dave than anyone else
the question of what is or wasn't what
isn't ergotic
seems to interact a lot with scale
and this is something that can be
manipulated
in an organization uh sometimes to
what seem like contradictory or
paradoxical effects
for a long time the us military officer
corps
has had an up or out policy
if you didn't get promoted within a
certain amount of time
you were invited to leave the military
and go do something else with your life
which sometimes didn't work well you
started running into
um the um uh
oh you know the the the british
sociologist from the 50s with
the famous organ the most famous
organizational law
such and such as law yeah people are you
know they end up in their
their at their level of incompetence
well much more recently just over 20
years ago the u.s department of justice
started adopting an up or out
policy which
quite likely is a lot more toxic
than having that in the military because
the military has
usually a fairly narrow kind of
purpose if it's being used at all in the
department of justice the fbi especially
if you're a local investigator you're
expected over a period of years
not just to know your colleagues and the
cops
and the prosecutors and the reporters
and the informants
and the way the underworld works whether
you're stomping them
or not you're expected to develop an
enormous amount of
highly differentiated knowledge of
south cincinnati or the east
bronx well then in the late 90s somebody
decided oh
no wait a minute this has this leaves a
possibility of local corruption
we're allowing nests of incompetence and
nests of bribery
so we're going to require people to
leave no matter how much you
love working in the south bronx you
either
get promoted to washington or you get
out
so some the intention presumably was to
keep a nice
smooth pipeline
a clear flowing stream but you end up
requiring incompetence instead
is there a larger scope at which
you become scale independent and that
sort of thing
and oh yeah it looks muddy at a low
level but it's actually ends up being
clearer or is it just
screwing up
question there's a lot there one piece i
kind of
heard is like there's systems that we
can actually control
like a software program we can write a
program
with a strictly defined topology of
variables
and so it's easier to take a realist
interpretation
of a program where we can define
all the pieces and we can know
everything that's happening but once
we're dealing with systems that
we didn't directly control we know that
we're dealing with
a map territory distinction
which i guess is something i'll flip to
because this
was just a great in a very accessible
point
which is wherever we go down the rabbit
hole with the math
we have to keep that map territory
embodied
metaphor in mind when whether it's a
phone you're looking at and
it's deep learning and it's maps and
recommendations or whether it's a
hand-drawn map
that your friend made or whether it's a
historical painting
it's a map and we can all see how that
differs than the actual
quote realism of the territory which
isn't even like what we
see it's actually something a little bit
else
so going uh and holding to this map
territory
distinction is kind of a useful thing
and so it's great that you brought it up
also on the sort of symbolic and
evocative wavelength
um what about the title or what inspired
the title
how did you see that story or that
narrative play out because you say a lot
with a few words
i think we stumbled on upon the title
and just thought it was too
too good not to use but in terms of the
uh what you have there oh goodness
um i i i heard you uh
uh uh uh explained the story during the
the pre-recording which is very
uh nice uh but i think there was one
element there
that you that you that you didn't
mention
and that's there that there are somehow
these these these swindlers in this
story
fell to the rest of the the lackeys and
so in the palace like these are a set of
clothes
that you can only that you can't that
you
can only see if you're very clever if
you're if you if you're too dumb you
won't be able to see these clothes
so there is and all the lackeys and
everybody involved in the story there
there is a kind of
doubt like is this me am i too stupid
or is something fishy going on here and
i think that kind of state of suspense
of not really knowing
i think that's perhaps the the key to
the title uh we don't we
well knowing to suggest that there were
swindlers in this story or so but that
kind of idea like hey
am i am i too stupid to get this or is
something weird going on and i think
uh uh everybody on everybody working on
free energy principle has or at least
should have
had that feeling to to to some extent uh
so i think that's the key to the
the title without giving away uh too
much about the rest of the story
yes shannon
i somehow missed that nuance from from
the title
um but it seems really question for
the new paper that just came out too and
um
the twitter post response on it too is
maybe certain technical aspects of the
free energy principle
weren't described with the specific
mathematics and formalism that you need
to properly criticize the free energy
principle
um which maybe maybe you do maybe you
need to have
that much detail to properly criticize
it but
if it's a principle that we want
to use in our empirical science and our
understanding of
whatever subject matter we're looking at
and also
something that we want to use i
i assume that in science we want to use
this to also inform the world
about something that we know about the
system that we're studying
um whether it's something like this is a
true real fact of the system or this is
the most useful way that we can
understand
the system so that we can apply
treatments you know maybe translate to
applied clinical practice or something
like that
then at some point it needs to be
possible
to abstract away from the formalism
without
losing the detail
or without losing the assumed detail
that the formalism brings in and
maybe it's just maybe like we have to
work through this nitty gritty stuff and
we have to fight over
very small mathematical details and
people that are better at math than i
have to make that fight before like we
can bring it in and
people in applied practices and
maybe even the greater public can start
understanding
exactly what this means
but i don't know when it when is the
point that we can get there what is the
point that we can say
okay we're done arguing about the
formalism we know there's subtle
differences
but i can still have a conversation with
my friend who's just interested in my
phd work but hasn't done a phd
themselves
or something like that i'm going to stop
talking as i start trailing off with
less points here but
just throwing that out there thanks
shannon cool points
manuel so
i hope this doesn't come along as a say
like
negative um uh perspective
in a way but i guess that beyond uh what
shannon mentioned already
as being part of the problems which are
real
which are absolutely real like when do
when can we stop
like getting into the nitty-gritty stuff
so that we can actually do some work on
top of that
and here i'm gonna break allowance like
in um like for freezing
like for once where i say that you know
part of what makes this job difficult is
also like the
um the idea of dealing with definitions
that
use the same words across different
fields
so we have an example here for uh with
ergodicity
so the ergodicity definition the
physicist
study is um yeah this idea of having
a system that visits all of the spa all
of the state in
um uh in a state space such that you can
replace time average with ensembl
averages
if you look at it from the perspective
of markov processes
which i think they've actually brought
out at some point
a periodicity actually becomes
a part of the definition if you look at
it from the perspective of ergotic
theory which is this field
born like 70 80 years ago and that
actually
is supposed to just be the uh to just
deal with their girdicity
then what they've actually suggested in
their field
is weak mixing so you can have
systems that are not ergotic sorry that
other gothic but not weak mixing
um so all in all without going like too
much into details i'm just trying to
suggest that there is also
a level of misunderstanding that comes
from people having different backgrounds
so on top of just say understanding what
is going on
we also need to have i don't know a
paper or two
that just list definitions as
you know i'm using this definition from
this specific field
you can find it in this book
[Music]
different people might want to say well
this is not really how i was taught this
but this specific concept
but at least it is something that i can
engage with
so a lot of the confusion especially on
ergodicity actually comes out just
of you know people having different
backgrounds none of them are wrong
because all of them are just using
different definitions
unfortunately totally agreed with that
it's almost like a scientific project
and
what we're seeing is that there's an
enormous desire to contribute to a
shared
scientific project and to make these
ideas not just something that
rests in the head of an expert but
something in our exocortex
in our informational niche something
where we can all just
see the affordances in a bigger project
like wikipedia
and improve it and then in service of
that
we need um alignment on really the
tools and the people and the ideas and
the ideas are more on the philosophical
side and the tools as we're seeing
are more on the technical side and
something that's right at the
intersection of tools people and ideas
are really the terms and their
definitions
and that pursuit of clarity as well as
improved ability to translate and
generate introductory material
is really key and that active inference
ontology
type work is one of the things we're
working on in actin flab
because we totally agree when there are
multiple definitions
then it's either a don't ask don't tell
policy on definitions or people do go
into the details and then the paper is
criticized for
providing a specific detailed take or
they make nine out of ten points but
then it
leaves um a shadow of doubt about the
tenth of tenth point
because it seems like it's going too
technical and when people do a linear
regression or a time series model
even when lives are on the line no one
says
wait a minute i need the least squares
error to be real
but we're seeing criticisms about what's
real here
and so that's such a fascinating pattern
that really
will be explored i think in the coming
months and years this
line of research has brought us to some
fundamentals and we are
bringing up some new questions and
connecting ideas and terms in new ways
so it's
fun to be a part of and um i hope that
those who are listening can
see that they're a part of this active
conversation
and it's not like they um the authors
released this paper and now the
conversation is over
this is sort of their opening call
and i hope that we can hear a few more
pieces about
what does that call entail for those who
take it up um yellow
yeah great um i just want to briefly
follow up on on on shannon's point
and uh saying that at least i think our
aim is also
to to uh um
to kind of tease apart a little bit the
kind of empirical
research program of of active inference
and
dcm and so and the more kind of
what we in the paper in the end called
the kind of most ambitious version of
blanket oriented ontology
and and show that uh you don't
need to buy into that heavy duty
metaphysical framework in order to do
empirical interesting
empirical work with active inference or
with with dcm or so
so that kind of association back and
forth
uh there might be a good fit uh but
there there's
i think there's very good reasons to
just say or marker blankets stay in my
cool toolkit as a scientist and i can
use them and employ them every once in a
while
but uh i'm not gonna speculate about how
how that that my toolkit fits onto
reality etc right
that's that's a different ballpark but
as having it in your toolkit you can
still do
uh basically all the signs that that
that's
already so i just want to be clear that
at no point do we want to say like oh
people should do empirical work
differently or so but it's really like
if you want to use this toolkit to dive
into
a different set of questions rather than
the traditional empirical ones you can
ask with
questions about the democratic agents or
or so that that might
look a lot like the empirical one but
actually are not really
uh then you are confronted with a
different set of questions namely about
how does mathematics relate to reality
and so but
by no means do we want to kind of uh
block that and i think i mean a long
time ago i started physics right
and then if you if you over bs you get
discussions about are atoms real and so
right
and these are kind of right these are
the kind of questions that are just that
are just funny to raise and some people
have more or less patience with them
uh but ben by no means do any of those
questions block uh
the actual research in in physics
they're they're they're orthogonal to
each other and i think the same
holds for for for for
for neuroscience at least to some extent
if you if you want to interpret data or
so you know
use use a mathematical toolbox for that
then that's completely
metaphysically innocent in that so to
say it's just this this transition
that has happened that we that we have
doubts about to take issue with
cool thanks and anyone can raise their
hand
one thought on that is that the
structure
of the implementation of active
inference
models with a partially observable
markov decision processes
helps us separate out for example our
priors about different variables
our generative model our affordances and
our preferences
so using that model helps us distinguish
for example our aspirational beliefs
about how the world should be or what
we'd prefer from
the sort of reality on the ground with
what our affordances are
and almost at a higher level this is
where this discussion is coming
can we separate out our technological
affordances from our preferences for
example
that an integrated theory of everything
would be preferable that just makes a
theory better for it to be
more explanatory more predictive more
universal
more transferable across different
systems those are
preferences we might have over
distributions of scientific theories
but that's not quite the same thing as
what are our affordances and
we don't know all the affordances yet
there's theories that haven't been
invented there's frameworks that don't
exist yet
so how how do we make sense at the lower
level
and then also at sort of a higher meta
scientific level
have a discussion across different
frameworks
without trapezing into essentially
unknowable metaphysical
questions stephen and then anyone else
yeah i'd be interested one of the it
sort of relates a bit to what
dave was saying there about feedback
loops and
we had in the last session we had casper
hesp talking about some of the modeling
and there you have these kind of
cyclical
um iterative dynamics
at different scales of how you know how
fast or slow the kind of the churn
of um observations and
sensory states and maybe states of
belief and
such things so there's kind of a
cyclical patterns sort of in there
so just be curious how that cyclical
pattern relates also to other types of
feedback which is maybe a bit more
dynamic um or
just other types of feedback loops that
you might think might need to be thought
of
yeah um i see chris and manuel both with
henries
yeah am i on youtube go ahead uh
manuel if you have if you want to say
something directly to the last question
then go ahead
right so um my bad for actually
not covering that before but the idea i
guess that
um dave previously brought out and now
stephen um kindly uh reminded us about
like the
this idea of feedback loops uh there is
so let's say uh um i would say that
my background might be more from control
theory
in some sense so i do see the need
of uh considering feedback loops um
because you know there's the sort of
like bread and butter in control theory
there is also a sense however in which
um
i guess usually in control theory we
draw diagrams
but they are kind of you know
representations that will leave
there as in like well this is the type
of system i'm dealing with
it is some sort of like picturesque uh
say a view of what is actually happening
out there we are not
doing maths on the
say like the the diagram that we are
drawing
in i guess what is happening with
bayesian networks and why people are
so much say inclined to use them
uh is the is the fact that i guess
we can actually use bezel network to do
calculations
so the the work by perl which we briefly
mentioned in our paper
clearly not giving enough justice to the
entire say
framework you know is something that can
be used
on these models themselves so
in a way the
the directionality there the unrolling
of time
the idea of an arrow of time there makes
all of these calculations possible
it is by no means uh a way to say that
there will be
um um
say system
that there will be different systems
necessarily different systems at
different times
we may still choose to group certain
variables and say well this
is just how i don't know the environment
is evolving over time or
how uh an agent is evolving over time
and we might just call that environment
we might just call that agent
that's fine i guess but when it comes to
say do calculations with that graph if
we just start drawing loops
then time disappears
and time is what makes a lot of these
calculations actually work
uh at least say what the algorithms
that um you know dania also mentioned
uh with message passing on bazel
networks
uh that is what makes them work like the
fact that it is
clearly there are also algorithms for
cyclic
uh networks but they are more limited
they have some
say uh they have some stronger
assumptions
so i'm rolling time i i think is not an
incredibly
crazy assumption or an incredibly crazy
same method
to use there it is probably yeah
something quite reasonable
we are still saying there's a there's a
there's an agent that talks to an
environment and an environment that
talks to an agent
we're just trying to make that say
interaction explicit
as a process that happens over time
thank you steven than anyone else
yeah thanks for that that that feedback
and i suppose one thing that
the question that can come up is um
and i'm not sure if the pearl blankets
could do this or something that the
frist and blankets
gives you the possibilities if you're
dealing with
entropic information and
noisy kind of data that's coming in
an entropy can be like zero dimensional
it doesn't actually need to have a
dimension
and you can extract from that whereas in
other cases
you you're always working with something
which is like a channel coming in with
like a dimensional
data source which is somehow like saying
something about the thing out there
as opposed to something which can be
completely untethered
from the environment so i wonder you
know how that
that idea of being able to extract
shannon entropy
information might be a unique property
of
the fristen blanket or whether that
could be done in other ways
um so uh
i guess there are a couple of
considerations there like
exactly what would be extracting
information from what
uh because i mean this sounds a lot like
the
sort of like maxwell's demon type of
scenario
which um you know it's a well-studied
field
but it's also say possibly controversial
in some sense because well in physics
you don't need to ask certain questions
you just well there's a demon and i
don't and i'm not gonna tell you what
this demon is
i'm not gonna tell you how he does his
thing it just does it
and this is how you know things will
happen
um the the thing about you know
extracting information in the
blanket sense well here i want to walk
say
um a very fine line um
by saying that the
there are possibly issues with this
definition of the friston blanket and
they have been raised before and i think
martin beale
has pointed them out in a recent paper
and fernando rosas has also mentioned
them in his uh work on causa blankets
as a way to fix i would say fristen
blankets
in the sense that the information that
can be extracted
in those blankets
is not past information is just
information at one specific time step
because of this unrolling
it makes calculations easier but
the sort of conditional independence is
not only
uh in within a time step is also across
time steps
because of the markovian um
property of uh of this processes
and i want to make sure this is not
something that i first raised
this came from people like martin beale
fernando rosas and probably in first
place nathaniel virgo
um so uh and again all the credit goes
to them
so this idea of extracting information
is really
feeble for now it is not uh
it is not something that i would
actually you know bank on
in any way
cool so it's almost like it's said to be
a strength of the markov blanket or any
kind of blanket concept that it's just
one time slice at a time but you don't
get to
have the blanket and eat it too because
you can't have the
through time benefits and then say that
you're simplifying with something that's
only reading one
value at a time though there's also
probably a lot of technical details too
so chris and then anyone else raising
their hand
onion
uh here we go sorry so that was a really
nice exchange
and i think it also ties things back to
to to your point about the map and the
territory distinction
because uh one thing that we have like i
think
one of the intentions we had uh at least
definitely me and joe who unfortunately
isn't here
but is very interested in these topics
is then is the philosophy of science
behind the notion of a scientific model
and one thing that we have to like in if
we frame things in this way it becomes
very interesting
how we understand persistence formalism
such as mark of blankets for example
because uh in philosophy
there's often this distinction made
between the model
the construal and the target system of
the model right so the target system
of the model is a phenomenon we're
trying to investigate in the world
the model itself is some kind of a
formal construction
usually usually described in some formal
language
and then the construal is kind of the
interpretive link that connects the
formal structure to the concrete
real world phenomenon and one
interesting thing about this
is that the same formal structure the
same model can be applied in different
fields
by different scientists successfully
using different construals right
and this also goes back to something
that manuel mentioned before about the
multiplicity of backgrounds from which
people come
to the free energy framework active
influence framework
and it's not unproductive i mean we have
good examples in the history of
science in the history of computer
science specifically
of people parting certain notions from
physics specifically into computer
science and making breakthroughs so one
very nice example of this is the
so-called icing model of ferromagnetism
which has been ported by william little
and john hopfield
into the neural network domain
where they basically used the same
formal structure
to and gave it a different construal
right to model a different a different
worldly phenomenon so hobfield networks
and later boltzmann networks have been
very successful for example in modeling
memory at least back when they were
introduced now we have
much more sophisticated models of course
but it's a nice
example of this kind of
cross-insemination between fields where
people can actually take a formal
structure or notion from one field and
successfully
make progress in a different domain but
one thing that's important to keep in
mind is that
you know little or hopfield never
never never never published their neural
network model and said like look
it's a thermodynamical model of memory
or something like that
because it's not i mean in a sense
of course it is because it's the the
formal
structure that has been mapped onto the
target
phenomenon is the same as in the icing
model or the spin glass model
the the thing is though that the
construals are very different and i
think it's
it's very useful to to to keep this in
mind
um it can so it could like to
boil my point down i guess the two
sentences it can be productive
doing this um it's just something that
we really wanted to bring to the surface
uh that we have to be aware of the
distinction between the thing in the
world
and the mathematical formula that we're
using to describe this thing in the
world
awesome thanks for this summary and
as people i think learn and read these
papers
they'll see that there are these
expanding levels of analysis from like
the one sentence don't confuse the map
with the territory
or what you just said there it can be
productive you just have to raise this
discussion to the surface
and then there's more and more and more
to uncover um kind of like chipping away
at the base of the pyramid almost and
finding out what are
our assumptions and okay all these
people criticizing elements of
free energy principle or active
inference what's their preference
what do they want to see or are we all
on the same aspirational team
in that we all want to see a
collaborative formal framework that also
might help us with real world questions
and also philosophical ones
variously stephen then anyone else
yeah i think this is this is a really
good conversation and i think
when i've heard other approaches say in
the psychology
fields which are kind of looking at how
people
do sense making they often outside of
work with the free energy principle it
tends to be
energy gradients people you know what's
the
route to least action or whether you
notice the energy is
lower so then you know how to act on the
environment
and of course the the ability to also
bring in
entropic kind of noisy
statistical regularities which you
wouldn't necessarily
know why they're there um
well you wouldn't know why they're there
we no one knows they're there we can't
even
understand it there's something quite
interesting and that seems to be
um where to my understanding i don't
know if there's any other models that
are able to
integrate the um
the energy landscape with this kind of
um
uh actual you know way to infer
something plausibly
from the entropic dynamics that are
played out
thanks steven blue then anyone else with
a question
so just to go back to what daniel was
saying about
incorporating the active inference
framework do we want this really to be
a framework that is concrete and
definite and stable do we want to come
to some kind of
absolute end point here with with active
inference or
is this something that we want to be
constantly evolving
growing changing do we want to try try
applying it like in several different
fields
seeing what works and what doesn't to
then then move on
so we have to think as we ask ourselves
and as we you know discourage and
encourage how the active inference
framework is used what do we really want
as scientists i think it's important to
think about that
great question blue really something we
could
all think a little bit about shannon
than
anyone else sort of um following up but
a little bit tangential what blue just
mentioned
um and maybe joe can be here
next week that would be great um but i'm
wondering if we're having sort of an
emerging
folk active inference um so we have a
like folk psychological intuitions about
the world about how other people behave
science uses slightly different maybe
more complex intuitions to describe
um how people perceive interact um to
describe the psychology of individuals
i'm wondering if
this active inference concept is really
great um how daniel talks about how we
work
in teams and how we're working together
to resolve our uncertainty and we're
coming together
in this um this
markov blanketed group of us compared to
everyone who
will be watching this live stream later
and these are fruitful
to making good team dynamics and to help
learn
and um some of us who aren't here right
now are applying this to
systems to business and organization and
this is super useful it's not the goal
of the scientists perhaps um
but maybe we can bring this up again
next week and just talk about
how that's useful and how that's sort of
emerging at the same time as these
formalisms
thanks shannon and i agree that um the
team and the project
and the mission sometimes sidestep or
at least um ward off the philosophical
questions it's like well let's finish
this project with this data set we have
get the publication or get this next
checkpoint
and then we'll see where we're at we'll
have a new perspective on these
eternal philosophical questions and so
it won't be resolved in
2021 maybe not even in 2022
but we'll be working together and we'll
be more productive and we'll have
stabilized our
informational niche our financial niche
dave
then anyone else
dave dave
he's still muted but
okay okay anyone else want to uh
add something
uh i was just gonna say like something
very briefly like um
concerning what blue uh brought out
which i think is um
very fair i guess uh view of
um a very fair perspective of you know
the the current status
of people that might choose to work on
active inference
there is a good cluster i guess of
people from
different backgrounds that have some
more or less shared goal
that are ready to you know engage with
each other
and try i guess like to create something
good with each other so
if anything else that that's great i
mean
what else would you actually need to do
science if not just a bunch of
you know motivated people that get
together
and try to to work towards something
altogether
um something that you know might have
just
um on the other hand push people away
uh like at different stages in time was
you know
the the idea of promising something that
was not really there yet
in a way like the nobody would blame
i guess anyone for for a project that is
just in the workings for something that
is evolving
for something that is still you know
that has still not reached
its final form
i guess the idea of reading you know a
theory a unifying theory of this a
unifying theory of that
is what might have you know discouraged
other people from from actually engaging
with it so
probably some sort of balance that i
think is now in place
is conducive to i guess
an even better research environment
because i think more people can
engage more people can see that there
are you know constructive criticisms
more people can see that you know it's
not just
uh you know a sort of environment
completely detached
from from reality there is there is a
sense in which you know
uh improvements happen when people
engage
and other people listen and you know
propose new stuff
which you know just a scientific method
that's absolutely fine that's great
i think we we had some very welcoming
you know uh feedback from different
people
like regardless of what we said
which i thought you know is good for a
healthy community
nice i think yeah thank you yeah a
mentor
in writing told me that the three stages
were the madman
the architect and the interior designer
so someone has to envision there could
be
a skyscraper here or there could be a
stadium here
and then it has to get planned out and
interior design has to be kept in mind
but
it isn't actually applied and so not
that those are the stages of a
scientific theory
but we're closer to the beginning and
you're right
that now there actually is enough to
kind of take a bite
out of and to build within and then for
those who think that there's like
little grounding or they want to make
almost hyperbolic claims about how
little is known
um my questions would be first off
relative to
which body of literature that's ongoing
and the second question would be
have you read the 2007 spm textbook
because that was 14 years ago
and it demonstrates in a little bit like
a textbook form which is more classical
than the pre-print
back and forth that's a lot of the basis
and so there isn't any philosophy in
that textbook but you'll find a lot of
new approaches for thinking about
cause and effect and dynamic systems
modeling and what we can do with
neuroimaging
and behavioral data and heterogeneous
data sets so
awesome points um dave if you want to
unmute and try again
and then blue
i'm i'm not sure why you're still muted
dave
there we go okay yep okay
um one of the really
crucial benefits of doing the
deconflation
that you are correctly insisting on is
that the real essence of
what's in
scientific thinking or technical
thinking or skill development is the
analogies
among different realms of thought realms
of action
if you conflate um
entropy with
the universal tendency you don't see
you can't think about the actual
differentiations
of instruments that should that measure
entropy
cosmological ideas that
discuss and structure our thinking about
a different
realm of activity and you certainly
aren't going to see the analogy between
those analogies
but once you start pulling stuff apart
then you can start doing mapping
in detail and find what
applications you can relate
through the instrumental
or realistic interpretation of any of
these meta concepts
you can start listing tables of
correspondences you can make
uh gadonkan experiment and you can make
literally lab tests and
draw out paradoxes where the prediction
from
one wing of the metaphor looks like it
ought to align
with another with the results in another
wing and don't
at that point now you can start thinking
about what it is that we don't know yet
so yeah yeah quick
quick keep keep ripping the stuff apart
when it's been conflated flogistan
modeled a lot of real stuff and it was
also
harmful the notion that things fall
because they belong down
that predicted a lot of things that
modeled a lot of stuff and
interfered with
work that needed to be done thank you
thanks steve
nice points blue
this is great because it just ties in
everything that dave said but i really
wanted to
respond to manuel um so
you know i don't necessarily have a
perspective on
whether we want active inference to be
something solid and concrete like a law
or something that's continually growing
and evolving and so i i just pose it as
a question
like where do we really want it to to
end
um i think that um just like dave said
you know there's always like we we had
the laws of physics right like newtonian
physics we had all these laws
they were in place they worked for a
long time and then quantum
right so so i mean we don't know what is
going to be underneath
when we when we finally define an
absolute there could be another layer
that we just aren't seeing yet
so i think that um you know just like
newtonian physics
and quantum physics we need to look at
where
the context is right and so there might
be an active inference
a a contextual barrier that we can say
you know active inference
is this version of active inference is
applicable
in this context and there might be some
other deeper
different version that applies in other
contexts
cool and i think that's partly
how the the specific projects and
deliverables and questions are what
ground us
like with dave's example about entropy
yeah you can probably
abstract entropy and start applying it
to different domains and
what would psychological entropy what
would spiritual entropy be
or you might be concerned with the car
that you're building
and you're like okay i have a preference
for the more miles per gallon and
less of this other emission and then
entropy in an applied context
is being pursued instrumentally
with literal instruments and scientists
are not just
all-purpose thinkers when the scientist
is on
were instrumentalists and actually that
makes me curious yella about one of your
other
papers the anticipating brain is not a
scientist
so what was that about because the part
in this paper about how the cognitive
scientist
is in a unique position as the meta
modeler
reminded me a lot of this line of
research so maybe
could you summarize that or what was
that paper about and how has that been
developed and what you're exploring now
oh great yeah um
so uh yeah i think and
can you hear me hey yeah i've got a
comment
um i only now realize that they used the
scientist metaphor uh
in both this paper and in in the in the
old one
uh and
i think here it's very clear to
distinguish between
models and models of knowledge models
and animals models and scientists models
and they have different kind of
properties in
in the anticipating brain paper
we make the same distinction between the
scientists model of the environment
and an animal's model environment and
there the distinction is more
in terms of what are the the aims so to
say of the model
and where you might say well in the
epistemic practice of science then the
aim of
the scientist model is to get an as
accurate
representation or inference or whatever
from the outside world as possible so it
is kind of a
more epistemic process in which the
ultimate aim is to
to figure out something about the world
and now
transposing that question to the uh to
the animal
the problem is a different one it's not
like the problem
what's out there in the world is
secondary to how can i make what's out
there in a world compatible with
the kind of existence that i am having
or am
and so there the epistemic story stands
in the surface of something like
flourishing or staying alive or
homeostasis or so and there might be
cases where actually
and i think this is also related to the
kind of the theory of action that's
there like
where uh inferring what's
the exact state of the world is not
actually the right thing to do
but changing the world so as to make it
conform to your expectations is the
better
way to do that so so that the kind of
the epistemic
aims in both settings the scientist
setting and the animal in his
environment setting are
are what the the scientists in this
everyday life setting are
are slightly different and so that was
also to counter the kind of
very prevalent kind of helmholtzian
models of perception that are there in
the in the
energy literature and and the processing
literature
where you say like well first and
foremost a problem for an agent or any
agent is to
infer what's out there in the world and
i think fep shows like no that that's
that's a secondary problem the first
problem is
staying alive
interesting and that's so funny because
what do they say
in legacy science publisher parish so
it's also not
thrive and communicate and mentor it's
actually
still phrased in a life or death way
that's all this might be and then the
eve wave understanding signs indeed that
might be true
yeah yes alliteration plus
competition just irresistible
any other thoughts otherwise there's a
couple other
points that would be awesome to kind of
just in the last 20 minutes
open up and then i'll re-upload
this full video we can all think about
some questions that we're having i guess
one distinction that
is clearly key from where you place it
in the paper and the emphasis and
everything
is inference with versus inference
within a model and this is gonna sound
like a subtlety because it's two letters
that you're appending to the word but
they're two letters that make
a big difference so what would be sort
of the map territory
distinction how do we think about
inference with and within a model how do
we speak
clearly about different things that are
happening
who's going to take that one
shall i okay okay good
i think i i insisted on keeping in this
distinction
throughout all phases of the co-writing
process so i guess i'm responsible for
now also
explaining it coherently um
i think the key distinction there is is
to draw the distinction between a kind
of
everyday wave understanding modeling
of saying well a model can be used by
something external to the model
to model something that's even external
to that right so i guess perhaps the
notion of construal might actually also
be something right there is there's
there's there there's a scientist or
there there's a practice or so that
construes
and relates a model uh uh
to some target phenomenon so that you
can can do a predictive analysis or
or whatsoever uh and i think that's our
everyday
way of thinking about scientific
inference
um and then especially in the in the
live as we know it papers at the first
in 2014
uh paper something quite different
is is is happening right so so in most
of the predicted processing literature
this distinction that really made made
that explicit but in 2013
that analysis is is
not making clear how an agent or an
animal can use a model to do something
but shows makes a model and shows how
somehow within that model a demacation
between
agent and environment starts to emerge
and because of the demarcation
uh uh an inferential relationship
between
agent and environment starts to emerge
so there's now there's not
there's not a user of that model but
somehow within a model
their inferential relationship starts to
starts to emerge and and so that's what
we call the inference within
a model the the emergence of the
inferences within that model
and the other one is something outside
of the model is using the model to
predict something or
capture something that that's supposed
to be this distinction maybe
maybe we'll think about a a better a
clearer
semantic separation between those two
concepts that should be
could be a part cool in the
four different kinds of
i guess i want to say processes but
the four different ways in which
inference is sometimes deployed to be
talking about generative processes and
generative
models you know the generative process
is what
actually the air moving through the
house and the temperature as it's
actually changing
and then the generative model the
predictive thermometer
and there's other work that i know some
of you have done
about connecting systems that are
probably less than
lifelike and realizing that we can frame
them
in a cybernetic context using these
um same constructs which is really an
argument by demonstration
almost about the philosophical points
that you're trying to show
it's like if somebody were making big
claims about cybernetic systems and then
someone said oh but it applies to a
thermometer
so either you need to pull back your
claims a little bit or
it's fine if you think thermometers have
this attribute like regret
that you're going to be studying but you
don't get to say that the thermometer is
of course insentient yet it's doing what
you say
is granting us sentience and these kinds
of distinctions
are not within active inference proper
it's actually just about clarifying
research directions
and learning about how we work on these
projects that go beyond
the understanding of one person because
there are a lot of technical elements so
kind of um remind us of that earlier
thread which is how are we all going to
be
learning about this and working within
it and communicating within it
when one could go deep into variational
inference but
you know i'm not going to be the one to
find that there's some deep quirk
or assumption and variational inference
that invalidates some other technical
piece of the puzzle so how do we almost
um
kind of like the the doors in the
titanic like separate
different parts of our model so that we
at least know
if one of them is going to be
unsupported at this moment
or is is apt to even fail
that the the there isn't a cascading
failure
for our actual direction but rather
there's something that's modular
that could be pulled out
yeah i think there's lots of things that
are lots of things about
energy principle that are actually
pretty trivial and some
lots of things that are actually pretty
uh speculative and
high stakes and and indeed having some
of the democrats that we make in our
paper
i guess allows you to separate some some
empirical methods that are
that are useful and and and kind of
non non non-controversial uh
separated indeed from from what we call
boo
uh the kind of blanket oriented ontology
which is uh
a big idea which we which we are kind of
skeptical about uh at least
i am i'm not sure i speak for all the uh
uh
uh co-authors but at least it has a
different epistemic stages than the
everyday bread and butter
active inference that people are using
and so separating those out a little bit
uh using the different concepts and
different assumptions that are made by
each
each approach uh probably also can give
gives a better overview of the field and
the things you need to buy into and
don't necessarily need to buy into if
you want to work with
cool um dave then anyone else raising
their hat
yeah i'm going to ask a question not
about
status or stature or number of papers
what influence has the personality
of carl fristen had on the development
of these fields
i want to go and break another lunch
like
in in his favor um
i haven't worked like directly with carl
uh unless like on really small projects
but he is just an extremely nice and
kind person
i think it is as simple as that like it
is really hard
not to to get along with them on some
level
so i mean i want to be positive in a
sense to say that
it is really hard not to
not to want to work with with such a
nice person
if we want to talk about that like
trying like to stay away say from
from his influence and his you know his
status across fields it's just an
incredibly nice person
and even if sometimes you know there are
some misunderstandings in communications
there is
i don't know uh there is a sense in
which
you feel like you want to work with that
person
i agree and also beyond niceness it is
reflected
through action and and mentorship and
collaboration
but also it's yes yellow and anyone else
as well
you know i can only uh uh second that i
i spent some time
in uh at ucl in in in this group
i guess for for
for outsiders and for brandings so you
might think sometimes that that carl is
able to speak a bit
uh too well right so listening to him
if you don't really understand what he's
saying it sounds
it sounds enigmatic it sounds it sounds
fascinating
and it sounds it is but it also sounds
incredibly clever right and so
um uh i guess in terms of branding right
i mean
what what what we see a lot now is that
there is a kind of
uh circle of people who really
understand the stuff that's going on
and and a group of people who are also
put off by it a little bit because
it it seems so intimidating from the
outside and and uh
i think that that's something that fpp
as a whole kind of struggles with a
little bit
uh uh that it might seem a little bit
esoteric if you're if you're not
familiar uh
uh uh with with with the keywords with
haven't worked on that for for a while
uh and i think that that's probably
sparkled but just these these kind of
fantastic uh
lectures that carl's able to get they're
all over youtube and so
and they're they're they're they're hard
to get on the first go
yeah and it's also notable
that the 2013 single author
paper life as we know it um
it serves as a lightning rod for a lot
of critique as does his 2010
paper uh unified brain theory
and they're both i hesitate to call them
old
because they're less than you know a
decade old in some cases but
in terms of our current environment
there's been a lot between then and now
and also their single author and so
let him speak and represent what he
wants to share
just like every author and collaboration
and then there's a ton of nuance and a
lot of development that's happened
and i totally also resonate with the um
criticism that many
raise or at least the point that it is a
rapidly developing field so it's like oh
active inference can't deal with long
time steps aha but then have you thought
about
sophisticated active inference and so it
does become
a little bit of this sort of like
criticism development criticism
development
which actually reminds me of daniel
dennett's book
darwin's dangerous idea and he says
evolution by natural selection
is the theory that's describing itself
because it is improving itself
and someone says well evolution doesn't
include ecology or development or
evolution okay well then we make ego evo
and then we go from there and so there's
sort of
um a little bit of a blurriness between
who's the detractor
and who's actually out in front pulling
the theory where it needs to be
and that's also where cognitive
diversity comes into play
and just we're all single
blue and then anyone else
so just to kind of piggyback off of what
you said i i always think
um you know especially in our culture
we have like this idea that there's a
leader or a creator
and in this situation it's carl fristin
right so
is there a leader or a creator of the
field or
has it become it's single-handedly
invented a light bulb that's not how it
happened but but we you know we kind of
think this way and we've kind of placed
first in in the leadership role here
but but really i think that there's a
lot going on underneath
the curtains or underneath the blankets
right
i agree and it's it's a meta
problem with science communication like
the 2018
wired article which the title be a
singular
person and about something about their
endocortex
not this dedicated researcher
has built a network and tools for 30
years
that are inspiring the next generation
of
researchers to make impact it doesn't
fit quite as well
in the headline and so it's like a
communication and a meta communication
question communicating about how these
uh fields actually
work and yeah there's going to be a lot
of interesting times ahead on those
frontiers i think
any sort of closing thoughts or maybe we
could go around and just give a
last little thought or something that
we're excited or curious about
for next week's discussion when i'll fix
it and we'll be able to include
participants live also thanks manuel for
for staying up late we'll have um martin
beale
on april 28th and that will be at um
a better time i think it's two hours
earlier than this one so
stephen then anyone else
yeah i'd just like to thank you for a
really you know
powerful presentation and answering a
lot of difficult questions and
also i suppose what i'll take away is
this question about the blanket
orientated ontology i think it's really
good to have that